Mss.B.F865
American Philosophical Society
John Fries Frazer papers, 1834-1871
Mss.B.F865
American Philosophical Society
3.0 Linear feet 6 boxes, ca. 683 items
Principal correspondents in the lettes of John Fries Frazer include Alexander Dallas Bache, Louis Agassiz, Joseph Henry, and Titian Ramsay Peale who discuss mainly general scientific topics, although personal and family matters are discussed with Bache. Topics include the University of Pennsylvania, boiler explosions, chemistry, education, the National Academy of Sciences, the Smithsonian Institution, fossils, magnetism, solar eclipses, the American Philosophical Society, weights and measures, the U.S. Coast and Geodetic Survey, scientific instruments, the American Civil War, electricity, the United States Mint, the Franklin Institute, scientists of the period, natural history, and publications.
Ca. 650 items.
Frazer, John Fries, 1812-1872
Box 1
Scope and Contents note
This collection consists of about 680 letters, most of which were exchanged between John Fries Frazer and various individuals between 1834 and 1870. Especially large groups are the correspondence with Louis Agassiz (22 items, 1849-1867), formerly B F865.a, and available as Film 1249; the correspondence with Joseph Henry (25 items, 1845-1871), formerly B F865.h, and available as Film 1249; the correspondence with Titian Ramsey Peale (27 items, enclosures, 1844-1854), formerly B F865.p, and available as Film 1249; and the correspondence with Alexander Dallas Bache and his wife Evey (238 letters and 1 photograph of the Union League of Philadelphia, 1844-1866), formerly B F865.b. Except for the letters from Guyot, Chollet, and Marcou (in French), the material is in English.
Many of the letters refer to Frazer’s work as a geologist as well as his leading role in several scientific organizations, such as the Franklin Institute and the American Philosophical Society. Moreover, many of the letters reflect Frazer’s efforts to support and publish the work of other scientists, a good number of whom were his personal friends.
The letters by Henry D. Rogers deal primarily with the Geological Survey of Pennsylvania. Rogers informs Frazer of his appointment as his assistant in the Survey on 13 April 1836; subsequent letters lay out in more detail what will be required of Frazer. The letter dated 1 January 1840 is a recommendation for Frazer. Other correspondents that write about geological matters include Trego, J. D. Graham, Hall, Emory, and Clymer, among others. Graham and Haldeman’s letters also refer to papers they submitted for publication in the Franklin Institute’s Bulletin and the APS Transactions. A letter that relates to efforts of the APS to support Kane’s polar expedition was written by the Academy of Natural Sciences, which also pledged its assistance (31 January 1853).
There are a few letters that shed light on Frazer’s interest in astronomy. They include the ones by Mifflin, which focus on botany and astronomy, as well as the two letters by Moses in which he refers to his instrumental examination of the Magnetic Observatory of Philadelphia. Norton similarly writes about magnetism (1 January 1847), and Wells inquires about the “focal length of the telescope belonging to [Frazer’s] institution” (28 September 1848). The letter by Hector Orr speculates that the moon travelled on a convex curve (25 December 1857). Of particular interest is a letter by Gillis addressed to Frazer and other leading scientists, in which he discusses in detail the regrettable failure of the Astronomical Expedition to measure the distance between the sun and moon (8 July 1859).
In general the letters reflect Frazer's broad and varied interests. For example, a letter by Trego asks Frazer for a manuscript containing the survey of the Mason-Dixon line in order to replace a boundary stone that has been “removed, destroyed, or lost” (28 February 1846). A detailed description of a newly invented “Ocean boat,” including several drawings, is given in the letter by James M. Price (5 August 1847). The letters by Haldemann deal with a variety of scientific matters, including the effect of heat on water pipes (20 March 1848). Evidence for Frazer’s habit of collecting specimens is included in the letter from Leighton (23 February 1854).
Frazer’s influence within scientific circles as well as his personal friendship with many leading figures in the field are well documented in the papers. A letter from Gould discusses a plan of several leading scientists, including Dana, Bache, Henry, and Agassiz, to meet as a group with “No name, no officers, no club, no society, no nothing, except one good happy annual winter feed” (22 November 1856). Several scientists asked Frazer for letters of recommendation and introduction in their efforts to secure teaching positions and establish contacts. Examples of such requests are the letter by Torrey that asks Frazer to write to the “Board of Education of New York what you think of my abilities as a chemist” (24 October 1848), as well as the request by Potter to support a “graduate of the University named Cummings (3 April 1850). The chemist F. A. Genth asked Frazer for support in his efforts to become Chemist of the State of Pennsylvania (26 January 1853). Another example is the letter by Haldeman that asks Frazer for a letter of introduction for John L. LeConte, who “has been seized with the sudden desire to go to California for purposes of science only” (8 November 1840). The growing popular interest in gold is evident in the letter from Boynton in which he asks Frazer for a loan of minerals for an upcoming lecture on gold, a topic that “rages here dreadfully” (14 December 1848).
Very few items deal with Native Americans. They include a letter by Haldeman, in which he discusses the characteristics of a bow used by “the natives living around Queen Charlottes sound, to take sea otters” (31 December 1839 - 1 January 1840). Also of interest is a letter by Joseph Henry that discusses publications relating to Native Americans (27 October 1855), and the letter by M. S. Henry that discusses the language of Delaware Indians (22 December 1859).
Material that relates to Frazer’s work as a teacher includes letters of appointment by the Athenian Institute (24 March 1840) and Franklin Institute (16 September 1840). The letter from Reese details Frazer’s salary for a lecture that was attended by twenty-four students (6 September 1848). Frazer’s interest in educational matters is also demonstrated by his election as chairman of the Association of the Friends of Education (28 September 1850). The Bache Committee of the Central High School recognized his contributions with his election as an honorary member (9 November 1850). Frazer also volunteered at educational institutions, as is suggested by the letter from the Logan Evening School for Young Men (13 April 1850).
One of Frazer’s close friends and frequent correspondents was Titian Ramsay Peale. The letters, which tend to be personal and candid, comment on a variety of people and topics, including Peale’s work in zoology and Louis Agassiz, a mutual friend. An amusing letter by Peale notes that his reading of the narrative of the Exploring Expedition led him to conclude that “we are a mite of nation.” He notes that the “people of our country are just like a big cheese, and allow the big worms to grow fat inside, while the mites are swept off with the dust on the surface” (23 July 1845). Finally, a few items, including letters by Roberts (3 April 1848) and Ingersoll (10 April 1848) relate to Peale’s efforts to get an appointment in the patent office.
Existence and Location of Copies note
Most of the material is included on Film 1249.
Related Archival Materials note
For papers of his father Robert Frazer, see B F868. For papers of his son Persifor Frazer, see B F867.
Early American History Note
John Fries Frazer was a prominent Pennsylvania scientist in nineteenth century America, serving as a professor at the University of Pennsylvania and very active in both the Franklin Institute and the APS. This large collection of his correspondence provides a snapshot of the growing scientific community in mid-nineteenth century America. Frazer’s correspondence involves a wide range of topics: science and scientific institutions (shipbuilding, mechanical engineering, geology, geography, astronomy, chemistry, among others), although there are fragments of personal correspondence. His range of correspondents is as diverse as the topics, but there is a notably large collection of letters from scientific heavyweights Titian Ramsey Peale, Louis Aggasiz, Joseph Henry, and Alexander Dallas Bache.
Combined with the Alexander Dallas Bache Collection and Titian Ramsay Peale Collection, the Frazer Collection lends insight into the American scientific community of the middle-nineteenth century and its increasing professionalism. Frazer worked under Alexander Dallas Bache, who was a mentor of sorts. T. R. Peale often discusses the internal politics of many early American scientific associations and institutions, offering insight into the personalities and conflicts within the American scientific community. There is a particularly large collection of Louis Aggasiz letters, which complements the APS Aggasiz Collection.
Although the collection is heavily weighted towards scientific discussions, Frazer was also active in Philadelphia’s civic life. For instance, he volunteered in the First Troop in 1844, which suppressed the anti-Irish riots. Some correspondence touches upon this aspect of Frazer's life, thus offering information on politics and culture in the antebellum period.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Received and accessioned, 1956-1957.
Biographical/Historical note
John Fries Frazer (1812–1872, APS 1842) was a scientist and educator. In the late 1830s Frazer took part in the Geological Survey of Pennsylvania, but Frazer’s contributions to science lay not in his own research but instead stemmed from his tireless and generous promotion and publication of other scientists’ work. He was a faculty member and provost at the University of Pennsylvania, a founder of the National Academy of Sciences, and a leading figure in the early history of the Franklin Institute in Philadelphia.
Frazer was the son of the eminent Philadelphia lawyer Robert Frazer and his wife Elizabeth Fries Frazer. Frazer spent most of his childhood in the care of various guardians, including his grandfather John Fries, who enrolled him in a military school in Connecticut. He was also a charge of the Reverend Samuel B. Wylie (1773-1852, APS 1806). Wylie taught the boy the classics and mathematics and, generally, prepared Frazer for his studies at the University of Pennsylvania. In 1830 Frazer earned his A.B. and three years later was awarded a semi-honorary M.A. from the university.
Frazer was a student and laboratory assistant of the scientist and educator Alexander Dallas Bache (1806-1867, APS 1829). It was during this period that Frazer made his only important original contributions to science; for example, he helped determine the relationship between the aurora borealis and magnetic forces. In his subsequent career as a scientist he would focus not on his own research but instead on the critical evaluation and presentation of other scientists’ work.
However, before Frazer dedicated his professional life to science, he took a short detour into the study and practice of law. Just when Frazer was scheduled to enroll in medical school, he decided instead to study law under William M. Meredith (1799-1873, APS 1837). He was admitted to the bar but practiced law only briefly before returning to science. In 1836 he was chosen as Henry D. Rogers’s (1808-1866, APS 1835) assistant for the Geological Survey of Pennsylvania. The survey ultimately resulted in many important geological discoveries, including the location of anthracite coal deposits in Pennsylvania.
In 1836 Frazer accepted a faculty position at the High School of Philadelphia (now Central High School). Six years later, in 1844, Alexander D. Bache resigned from the University of Pennsylvania. Frazer was selected to fill the vacancy as Professor of Natural Philosophy and Chemistry. At the time Frazer was the university’s youngest faculty member and the first professor specifically charged with teaching chemistry. He held the chair and other administrative position at the University of Pennsylvania, including that of vice provost, until his death.
Frazer’s interests extended beyond university life. He was an active member of the American Philosophical Society, elected to membership in 1842, becoming its secretary in 1845, and serving as vice president from 1855 to 1857. He resigned from this position in 1858, “owing to some unhappy differences which then distracted the Society,” as John L. Le Conte (1825-1883, APS 1853) explained in his “Obituary Notice.” Frazer was an early member of the Union League, and he helped found the National Academy of Sciences (1863). Furthermore, he was a leading figure at the Franklin Institute in Philadelphia. He was one of the Institute’s lecturers, and from 1850 to 1866 served as editor of the "Journal of the Franklin Institute". In 1856 and again in 1866, poor health compelled him to take sabbaticals and spend several months in Europe.
Frazer’s main accomplishments lay in his ability to select, evaluate and publicize the work of other scientists from the United States and Europe. He enjoyed the respect and friendship of leading scientists of the day, including the zoologist and geologist Louis Agassiz (1807-1873, APS 1843) and the entomologist John L. Le Conte. In 1838, Frazer married Charlotte Jeffers Cave (1815–1881). They had three children; his son Persifor, also known as Persifor, Jr. (1844–1909, APS 1872) became a prominent geologist and chemist who succeeded Frazer as the chair of chemistry at the University of Pennsylvania. John Fries Frazer died suddenly in 1872 while giving a tour of the physical laboratory of the University of Pennsylvania.
Agassiz, Louis, 1807-1873; Allen, George, 1808-1876; American Philosophical Society.; Bache, A.D., (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867; Barnard, Frederick A. P. -- (Frederick Augustus Porter), -- 1809-1889.; Booth, James Curtis, 1810-1888; Caswell, Alexis, 1799-1877; Davidson, George, 1825-1911; Emory, William H., (William Hemsley), 1811-1887; Fraley, F., (Frederick), 1804-1901; Gibbs, Wolcott, 1822-1908; Gould, Benjamin Apthorp, 1824-1896; Haldeman, Samuel Stehman, 1812-1880; Hayes, I. I, (Isaac Israel), 1832-1881; Henry, Joseph, 1797-1878; LeConte, John L., (John Lawrence), 1825-1883; Meigs, Charles D., (Charles Delucena), 1792-1869; Morton, Samuel George, 1799-1851; National Academy of Sciences. (U.S.); Peale, Titian Ramsay, 1799-1885; Peirce, Benjamin, 1809-1880; Reed, William B., (William Bradford), 1806-1876; Roberts, Solomon W., (Solomon White), 1811-1882; Rogers, Henry D., (Henry Darwin), 1806-1866; Rutherford, Lewis M.; Schaeffer, Charles Frederick, 1807-1879; Smithsonian Institution.; U.S. Coast and Geodetic Survey.; United States Mint.; University of Pennsylvania.; Wetherill, Charles Mayer, 1825-1871; Boilers.; Education; Education -- United States.; Electricity.; General Correspondence; Geology -- United States.; Magnetism.; Natural history.; Paleontology.; Philadelphia History; Science and Technology; Scientific apparatus and instruments.; Scientific Correspondence; Scientists -- United States.; Solar eclipses.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865.; Weights and measures.
- Correspondence
  - Table of Contents, B F865
  - Table of Contents, B F865.b, Alexander Dallas Bache Letters
  - Letter to John F[ries] Frazer, Philadelphia, April 28, [1834]; 10x8; Rogers, Henry D., (Henry Darwin), 1806-1866
    Scope and Contents note
    University of Virginia, A.L.S. 3p. and add. Friendly letter. Asks favors.
  - Letter to John F[ries] Frazer, Philadelphia, April 28, [1852?]; 10x8; Bache, A. D. (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867
    General note
    Film 1249.
    A.L.S. 1 p. and add. Formerly B F865.b. Concerning T.R. Peale. Refers to the APS.
  - Letter to [John Fries] Frazer, [1853]; 7x4-1/2; Merrick, S. V., (Samuel Vaughan), 1801-1870
    A.L.S. 1p. Enc. wanting. Business Concerning the Franklin institute.
  - Letter to [John Fries Frazer], [1853]; 7x4-1/4; Peter, Sarah
    Monday, 10th. A.L.S. 4p. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to [John Fries] Frazer, [1853]; 5x4; Peter, Sarah
    Monday. A.L.S. 3p. Concerning papers for publication. Refers to Fraley.
  - Letter to [John Fries Frazer], [1853]; 7x4-1/4; Peter, Sarah
    Monday. A.L.S. 4p. Asks favor.
  - Letter to [John Fries] Frazer, Sept. 5, [1853]; 5-1/2x3-1/2; Peter, Sarah
    A.L. in 3rd. P. 1p. Requests aid for the Franklin institute.
  - Letter to [John Fries] Frazer, Feb. 18, [1856]; 8x5; Bache, A. D. (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867
    Washington, A.L.S. 2p. Formerly B F865.b. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to P[eter] Cooper, Sept., [1857]; 8x5; Brown-Séquard, Charles-Edouard, 1817-1894
    A.L. 1p. Copy. Concerning a job at Cooper institute. Enclosed originally in letter from Brown-Séquard to J. F. Frazer; Sept. 17, 1857.
  - Letter to [John Fries Frazer], Nov. 21, [1857]; 8x5; Bache, A. D. (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867
    New York, A.L.S. with initials. 2p. Formerly B F865.b. Friendly letter. Refers to F.Rogers.
  - Letter to [John Fries] Frazer, [1863?]; 8x5; Bache, A. D. (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867
    Friday evening. [ca.]. A.L.S. with initials. 1p. Formerly B F865.b. Asks favor.
  - Letter to [John Fries] Frazer, April 16, [1867]; 8-1/4x5-1/4; Bache, Evey (Nancy Clarke Fowler)
    Newport, R. I., A.L.S. 3p. Formerly B F865.b. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to [John Fries] Frazer, April 28, [1867]; 8-1/4x5-1/2; Bache, Evey (Nancy Clarke Fowler)
    Washington, A.L.S. 3p. Formerly B F865.b. Friendly letter. Film 1249.
  - Letter to J[ohn] F[ries] Frazer, undated; 8x5; Cresson, Charles M.
    Wednesday. A.L.S. 1p. Are Leidy and Goddard invited to an exhibit?
  - Letter to [John Fries] Frazer, undated; 8x5; Cresson, Charles M.
    Friday. A.L.S. 1p. In pencil. Asks him to observe some experiments.
  - Letter to [John Fries] Frazer, undated; 12-3/4x8; Lee & Fisher
    L. 1p. Asks for a statement from him concerning a patent.
  - Letter to [John Fries] Frazer, undated; 8x5; Reed, E. W.
    Saturday A.L.S. 1p. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to [John Fries] Frazer, undated; 8x8; Wetherill, Charles Mayer, 1825-1871
    A.L.S. 1 p. Concerning his work on asphalt.
  - Letter to [John Fries] Frazer, undated; 9-3/4x7-3/4; Wetherill, Charles Mayer, 1825-1871
    Friendly letter. A.L.S. 1 p. and add.
  - Letter to [John Fries] Frazer, undated; 8x5; Reed, E. W.
    Sunday. A.L.S. 1p. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to John F[ries] Frazer, April 13, 1836; 10x8; Rogers, Henry D., (Henry Darwin), 1806-1866
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 1p. Appoints him assistant geologist for Pennsylvania.
  - Letter to John F[ries] Frazer, Meadville, June, 1836?; 10x8; Rogers, Henry D., (Henry Darwin), 1806-1866
    A.L.S. 3p. and add., end. Geology of Pennsylvania.
  - Letter to John F[ries] Frazer, April 12, 1837; 10x8; Rogers, Henry D., (Henry Darwin), 1806-1866
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 3p. and add., end. Instructions concerning the geological survey of Pennsylvania.
  - Letter to John F[ries] Frazer, April 12, 1837; 10-1/2x8-1/4; Rogers, Henry D., (Henry Darwin), 1806-1866
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 3p. and add. Instructions for the geological survey of Pennsylvania.
  - Letter to John F[ries] Frazer, May 17, 1837; 10x8; Rogers, Henry D., (Henry Darwin), 1806-1866
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 1p. Accepts his resignation.
  - Letter to J[ohn] F[ries] Frazer, Dec. 31-Jan.1, 1839-1840; 9-3/4x7-1/2; Haldeman, Samuel Stehman, 1812-1880
    A.L.S. 5p. and 1p. sketch of a facade of a house. Freeman Guide 1535. Concerning Indian artifacts. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to ----, Jan. 1, 1840; 13x8; Rogers, Henry D., (Henry Darwin), 1806-1866
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 1p. and add. Recommendation of J. F. Frazer as a geologist.
  - Letter to John [Fries] Frazer, Philadelphia, March 24, 1840; 10x8; Athenian institute (Philadelphia, Pa.)
    Philadelphia, L.S.: William B. Reed. 1p. and add. Asks him to lecture.
  - Letter to John F[ries] Frazer, Sept. 16, 1840; 10x8
    Philadelphia, L.S.: J. C. Cresson. 1p. Notifies him of his election as professor.
  - Letter to John Fries Frazer, February 7, 1841; Alexander, J. H. (John Henry), 1812-1867.
    Mentions missionary work among Native Americans. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to John [Fries] Frazer, Philadelphia, July 5, 1841; 9-3/4x7-3/4; Cable, J.
    Natchitoches, A.L.S. 2p. and add. Concerning geology.
  - Letter to John F[ries] Frazer, Philadelphia, June 17, 1842; 10x8; Trego, Charles B., 1794-1874
    Harrisburg, A.L.S. 3p. and add. Friendly letter. Concerning geology of Pennsylvania.
  - Letter to J[ohn] F[ries] Frazer, Philadelphia, May 30, 1843; 10x8; Mifflin, S. W.
    Wrightsville, A.L.S. 2p. and add. Concerning botany and astronomy.
  - Letter to John F[ries] Frazer, Philadelphia, June 13, 1843; 10x8; Mifflin, S. W.
    Wrightsville, A.L.S. 2p. and add. Concerning botany.
  - Letter to John F[ries] Frazer, Philadelphia, March 21, 1844; 10x8; Bache, A. D. (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867
    Washington, A.L.S. 2p. and add. Formerly B F865.b. Concerning the university of Pennsylvania. Refers to J. K. Kane, the APS and Ord.
  - Letter to John F[ries] Frazer, Philadelphia, April 18, 1844; 10x8; Bache, A. D. (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867
    Washington, A.L.S. 3p. and add. Formerly B F865.b. Friendly letter. Concerning water wheels. Refers to Ord.
  - Letter to John F[ries] Frazer, Philadelphia, May 15, 1844; 10x7-1/2; Peale, Titian Ramsay, 1799-1885
    Film 1249
    Washington, A.L.S. 3p. and add. Formerly B F865.p. Friendly letter. Refers to Audubon's "Birds", R. M. Patterson, and geology.
  - Letter to John F[ries] Frazer, Philadelphia, June 8, 1844; 10x8; Bache, A. D. (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867
    Washington, A.L.S. 1p. and add. Formerly B F865.b. Friendly letter. Concerning magnetism.
  - Letter to John F[ries] Frazer, Philadelphia, July 27, 1844; 10x8; Bache, A. D. (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867
    A.L.S. 2p. and add. Formerly B F865.b. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to [John Fries] Frazer, Philadelphia, Aug. 29, 1844; 9-3/4x8; Hall, James
    Albany, A.L.S. 2p. and add. Concerning geological maps. Refers to S. Rogers.
  - Receipt to the Magnetic observatory of Philadelphia, May 20, May 21, 1845; 4-1/2x7-1/4; Moses, Horace, 1820-1893
    Philadelphia, A.D.S. 1p.
  - Letter to John [Fries] Frazer, Philadelphia, Jan. 8, 1845; 12-1/2x7-1/2; Mifflin, S. W.
    Wrightsville, A.L.S. 2p. and add. Concerning astronomy.
  - Letter to John F[ries] Frazer, Philadelphia, Jan. 25, 1845; 10x7-1/2; Mifflin, S. W.
    Wrightsville, A.L.S. 1p. and add. Concerning astronomy.
  - Letter to John [Fries] Frazer, Feb. 24, 1845; 8x5; Hagedane, C. Y.
    A.L.S. 3p. Thanks for autograph of Washington.
  - Letter to John F[ries] Frazer, Philadelphia, May 18, 1845; 10x8; Bache, A. D. (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867
    A.L.S. 3p. and add. Formerly B F865.b. Concerning magnetism. Refers to S. C. Walker.
  - Letter to J[ohn] F[ries] Frazer, Philadelphia, July 23, 1845; 10x8; Peale, Titian Ramsay, 1799-1885
    Washington, A.L.S. 2p. and add. Friendly letter. Refers to the APS.
  - Letter to John F[ries] Frazer, Philadelphia, Sept. 12, 1845; 10x7-1/2; Henry, Joseph, 1797-1878
    Princeton, A.L.S. 3p. and add. Formerly B F865.h. Friendly letter. Concerning A. D. Bache and Sir John Herschell.
  - Letter to [John Fries] Frazer, Sept. 30, 1845; 10x8; Meigs, Charles D., (Charles Delucena), 1792-1869
    A.L.S. 1p. Thank you note.
  - Letter to [John Fries] Frazer, Nov. 2, 1845; 10x7-3/4; Graham, J. D. (James Duncan), 1799-1865